<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The valorous warrior's welfare, in God's victorious warfare A sermon preach'd in His Majesty's English camp, near the city of Ghendt in Flanders; before the battalion of His Royal Highness George Prince of Denmark, under the command of the right honourable Colonel Charles Churchill, major-general of His Majesty's forces in the Netherlands. By William Williams, minister of the Gospel, and a son of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Williams, William, Inferior Brother to the venerable and orthodox clergy.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2791</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219571</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831032</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831032</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35494</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66471)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35494)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2086:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The valorous warrior's welfare, in God's victorious warfare A sermon preach'd in His Majesty's English camp, near the city of Ghendt in Flanders; before the battalion of His Royal Highness George Prince of Denmark, under the command of the right honourable Colonel Charles Churchill, major-general of His Majesty's forces in the Netherlands. By William Williams, minister of the Gospel, and a son of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Williams, William, Inferior Brother to the venerable and orthodox clergy.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for John Pero, at the White Swan, and Edward Powel next the Pump-Coffee-House in Little Britain; and sold by R. Baldwin, near the Oxford-Arms in Warwick-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a final advertisment leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>George, --  Prince, consort of Anne, Queen of Great Britain, 1653-1708 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LX, 12 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35494:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Valorous Warrior's Welfare,</hi> IN <hi>God's Victorious Warfare.</hi> A SERMON PREACH'D In His Majeſty's <hi>Engliſh</hi> Camp, near the City of <hi>Ghendt</hi> in <hi>Flanders;</hi> Before the BATTALION of His Royal Highneſs <hi>GEORGE</hi> Prince of <hi>Denmark,</hi> Under the Command of the Right Honourable Colonel <hi>CHARLES CHURCHILL,</hi> Major-General of His Majeſty's Forces in the <hi>NETHERLANDS.</hi> By <hi>WILLIAM WILLIAMS,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel, And a Son of the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Pero,</hi> at the <hi>White Swan,</hi> and <hi>Edward Powel</hi> next the <hi>Pump-Coffee-Houſe</hi> in <hi>Little Britain;</hi> and ſold by <hi>R. Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane,</hi> 1696.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35494:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35494:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:35494:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35494:3"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>Moſt Magnanimous, Magnificent, and Munificent</hi> MONARCH, William the Third (By GOD's Providential Appointment) KING of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Sacred Majeſty,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN the loweſt degree of Submiſſion, I appeal to Your Regal Clemency for a Royal Pardon, in preſuming ſo Sublime and Supream a Dedication, being very conſcious of my Imperfections to manage this Great Enterprize: Yet conſidering that the meaneſt Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject hath ſome Intereſt in the Favour of his Prince, I em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolden'd my ſelf on that account to ſhelter the follow Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon under the Defence of your Royal Patronage; which at its Promulgation in your Majeſty's <hi>Engliſh</hi> Camp in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> gain'd the diligent Attention and Approbation of its Auditors. In purſuance whereof, I briefly manifeſted and maintain'd, The equitable Cauſe of your Majeſty's late and continued Wars with the Adverſaries of your Realms and Government; The indubitable Pleaſure of God in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and eſtabliſhing your Royal Perſon on the Thrones of our Three Kingdoms; The ſeaſonable Preſervation of our <hi>Britiſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Church, in the Principles and Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives thereof by your ſacred Defence of her Chriſtian
<pb facs="tcp:35494:4"/>and Catholick Faith; The profitable Wea l of our Nation, by your Princely and Puiſſant Aid, in ſecuring the juſt Rights and Liberties of Free-born Subjects; the innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Deliverances of your Secular, Civil, and Martial Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, from thoſe dangerous and deſperate Hazards to which you were often expos'd by the Fatal Peril of the Sword; And the incomparable Protection of your pious Perſon from the Deſtructive Deſigns of Sanguinary Aſſaſſinates, whoſe Aim (in all probability) was to ſubvert the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Theſe particular Inſtances, with the whole Matter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the Subject of my Warlike Diſcourſe (though delivered in a plain and familiar Method) I humbly Dedicate to the Condeſcention of your Royal and Favourable Peruſal; being a Pledge of that Impartial Love and Loyalty which ſhall be duly and daily paid to your Regal Authority, by him who is, according to thoſe Apoſtolical Rules, of Fearing God, Honouring the King, with Subjection for Conſcience, and Submiſſion for the Lord's ſake,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Great SIR,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Majeſty's moſt Obſervant Subject, and Obeyſant Servant,</hi> Wi. Williams.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:35494:4"/>
            <head>TO THE CAPITAL COMMANDERS, <hi>And All Other Military Officers,</hi> According to their Reſpective Poſts or Stations, Engag'd in the Management of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army, <hi>William Williams</hi> wiſheth,
<list>
                  <item>National, Perſonal, and Internal Tranquility.</item>
                  <item>Temporal, Subſtantial, and External Proſperity.</item>
                  <item>Spiritual, Immortal, and Eternal Felicity.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Valorons and Victorious Martialiſts,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT was the pleaſure of Almighty God, as being the Tutor of Valiant <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and other Famous Worthies, of Heroick Spirits, before he inſtructed them in the Art of Military Diſcipline, by teaching their Hands to War and their Fingers to Fight (being Atchievements fit for Combatants, and ſuch as are train'd in Gladiatory Affairs) to aſſume unto his Sacred ſelf the Champion Title of a Man of War, in <hi>Exod. 15.8.</hi> where his Servant <hi>Moſes</hi> declares in the ſame Scripture, that the Lord is his Name: Thereby importing that Power, Courage, Succeſs, Victory and Triumph, are all of them Endowments proper and peculiar to God alone; though by his Condeſcenſive and Permiſſive Pleaſure a communicative Reſpect in a participative manner (having its Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from himſelf) is ſupernaturally inſtrumental, in cauſing admiring Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals to Praiſe God, and to Blazon the Braveryes, Adorn the Acts, or Fame the Feats of Military Men. This ſort of Martial Honour eminently appear'd in the Publick and Princely perſons of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> whoſe magnanimous and magnificent Victories over their numerous Adverſaries embelliſhed the Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies of their Conquering Triumphs, with reſounding Acclamations of Royal Renown and Popular Applauſe, which as laſting monuments of their Hoſtile Exploits are Regiſter'd (to inform all Humane Poſterities) in the Canonical
<pb facs="tcp:35494:5"/>Chronicle of Sacred Hiſtories, witneſs the firſt Book of <hi>Samuel,</hi> Chap. <hi>29</hi> Ver. <hi>5.</hi> where it is reported—That the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſang one to another in Dances, ſaying, <hi>That</hi> Saul <hi>ſlew his Thouſands, and</hi> David <hi>his Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands,</hi> to Memorize the Fame of Fate and Fortitude.</p>
            <p>This Accompt of the Slain amounting to Thouſands, and Ten Thouſands, ſeems to intimate an unknown, innumerable, or numberleſs number; but as to the Armies or Militia that were deſtroy'd by the Generals, Chieftains, Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rions, and Soldiers of <hi>David,</hi> we find that the Divine Warriour aſcrib'd the Succeſs which attended his Arms and Weapons of Warfare, to the concurring and corroborating Power of God, as it is apparently evident in the words of my preſent Text, where he ſpeaks theſe Couragious and Religious Expreſſions, —<hi>Through God we ſhall do valiantly; for he it is that ſhall tread down our Enemies.</hi> The Valiant Acts here mention'd, or Valour derivative (in this Verſe from God to Men) I Chriſtianly Conjecture was Experimentally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd by many Worthies, to whom I Dedicate this Epiſtle, in their Warlike Enterprizes relating to the late Affairs of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> who with the reſt here hinted, may lay a juſt Claim to the Diſcourſe iſſuing from the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Subject; which having the Approbation of numerous attentive Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and alſo their Importunity to have it made publick for the Benefit of the Army, I have by forcible Obligations yielded to the ſway of prevalency, and adventur'd (as far as Moderation allow'd me) to comply with their reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Requeſt: And if it meet with ſome Thwarting and Carping Diſpoſitions of Captious or Conceited Criticks, too much intermedling and buſying themſelves in this Cenſorious Age, I aſſign Armed Men, whoſe Cauſe and Right it is, both to Patronize and Defend its Innocency, leaving ſuch Cauſleſs Quarrellers on the Forlorn Hope of doing Injury, either to Miniſterial or Martial Authority. In ample Satisfaction or full Aſſurance whereof, I commit the Army, the Fleet, my Self, and all that deſire the Welfare of our Three Kingdoms, to God's Gracious Protection and Providence; remaining,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Moſt Couragious Worthies, Your Devoted Friend and Servant,</hi> William Williams.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:35494:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Valourous Warriours Welfare, in God's Victorious Warfare.</hi> As it was Deliver'd in a SERMON PERTAINING To the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and Preach'd On Pſal. LX. Ver. 12. <hi>Through God we ſhall do Valiantly: for he it is that ſhall tread down our Enemies.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THIS <hi>Pſalm,</hi> whereof my Text is a part, was Compil'd by the Military Monarch <hi>David,</hi> when he and his Army waged War, or ſtrove with <hi>Aram Naharaim,</hi> and <hi>Aram Zoba,</hi> even at the return of <hi>Joab</hi> the Son of <hi>Zerviah,</hi> (who was a Chief Officer over the Hoſt of <hi>David</hi> (from ſlaying of the <hi>Syrians</hi> or <hi>Edomites</hi> in the Valley of <hi>Salt,</hi> to the number of Eighteen Thouſand Men. The Hiſtory of which Engagement, you may find Recorded in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.1, to 17. and alſo in 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18.1, to 16. in which Relation we may obſerve, that Holy <hi>David</hi> was very Succeſsful in his Warlike Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes, for he overcame many Potent Kings and Kingdoms, thro' a fixed Affiance in the Faithfulneſs and All-ſufficiency of an Infallible and Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent God, who is the moſt Magnificent Monarch, and Mightieſt War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith in <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.3. <hi>The Lord is a Man of War, the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35494:6"/>Lord is his Name,</hi> or his Name is <hi>Jehovah,</hi> which denotes both his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Hoſtility. This Military Deſcription of God may be fitly ſtil'd the Soldiers Armory or Magazine, where not only his Carnal, but alſo Spiritual Weapons, Accoutrements and Ammunition are conſtantly kept in a Warlike Readineſs: It is as it were <hi>the Tower of</hi> David, <hi>whereon there hang a Thouſand Bucklers, all Shields of Mighty Men,</hi> as you may Read in the 4th Chapter of <hi>Canticles</hi> or <hi>Song of Solomon,</hi> at the 4th Verſe: Or as that Tower of <hi>Solomon</hi> mention'd in <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.10. where it is ſaid, that—<hi>The Name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower, the Righteous runneth into it, and is ſafe.</hi> Therefore let us betake our ſelves to this ſtrong Citadel, or Invincible Gariſon, which is the Chriſtian Combatant's Fort Roval, where the Captain of our Salvation is Chriſt Jeſus, and the Generaliſſimo of our Believing Forces, God Almighty, whoſe Banner over us is Love, and that ſtronger than Death; for <hi>many Waters could not quench his Love, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could the Floods drown it,</hi> as you may note in <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.7. This is that Love which ſurpaſſeth Knowledge, whereof the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks in <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.19. The Superlative Tranſcendeney of which is apparently made manifeſt in the Miraculous and many Renown'd Victories obtain'd (over their Enemies) by the Adventurous Armies, and Couragious Champions of the Living God; under whoſe Irreſiſtible Power, not only Royal <hi>David</hi> in particular, but alſo his Loyal Hoſt in general, did Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorouſly reſolve to Encount or and Conquer their Adverſaries, yet ſo, as at the ſame time, and in the mean ſpace, that with one Unanimous and Harmonious Conſent, they voluntarily and devoutly aſcrib'd unto God, (to whom it was due) even the Glorious and Praiſe-worthy Succeſs of their Valiant and Vigorous Victories, according to theſe Heroical or Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Expreſſions of my preſent Text, where Divine and Undaunted <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> as it were after an Alarm to take up Arms, made this Conſolatory Speech unto his Army, <hi>Through God we ſhall do valiantly: for he it is that ſhall tread down our Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Portion of Scripture, being the Subject of my Warlike Diſcourſe, hath its Foundation laid on the moſt durable and unmoveable Rock of Ages, namely, God himſelf; and that by a Matchleſs Monarch of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to wit, the Militant and Triumphant <hi>David,</hi> in which Text, as a Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Town, or City of Refuge, he hath Erected on the Eaſt-ſide an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Caſtle of Safety, and on the Weſt an Holy Tower of Security: The Heavenly Caſtle of Safety, importing God's Favourable Preſence with his People, in Countenancing them to defie the fierceneſs of their Enemies, according to theſe former words of my Text, <hi>Through God we ſhall do valiantly:</hi> The Holy Tower of Security, implying God's power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35494:6"/>Providence to his People, in Encouraging them to Defeat the Forces of their Adverſaries, as concurring with theſe laſt Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in my preſent Subject, <hi>For he it is that ſhall tread down our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Through God we ſhall do valiantly: for he it is that ſhall tread down our Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In walking the Rounds of this Text, Town, or City of Refuge, which hath God ſeated in the Circuit, Situation and Centre thereof, for its Safety, as alſo Sallying the Ports, viewing the Rampiers, Platforms, Counterſcarps, Fortreſſes, Flankers, Battlements, Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks, and Batteries thereof. Beſides, a Caſtle and a Tower Erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Eaſtern and Weſtern ſides, to prevent the Storming, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing, Beſieging, Invading or Taking of the ſame by Force; I likewiſe diſcover'd it ſtrongly fortify'd on the North and South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, with two other Regal Citadels, or Royal Forts of Defence, and they are theſe which I ſhall deſcribe unto you.</p>
            <p>Firſt, King <hi>David</hi>'s Divine Conſideration, That the Foundation of a Juſt War in the Defence of his Peoples Lives, Laws, Liberties and Religion, hath its Victorious Dependency on the Supream Power and Providence of God, the which is apparently evident in the front of my preſent Text, where the purpoſe of God in preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his People from the violent Enterprizes of their Enemies, is thus Elegantly and Excellently expreſt, <hi>Through God we ſhall do valiantly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, King <hi>David</hi>'s Divine Suggeſtion, That tho' the People of God may be Inſtrumental in ſubduing their Enemies, yet the Succeſs that makes their Foes their Footſtool, is a principal Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive only peculiar to God himſelf: And this is likewiſe apparent in the Rear of my preſent Subject, where the pleaſure of God in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Peoples Adverſaries, is thus Emphatically and Pathetically worded, <hi>For he it is that ſhall tread down our Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Through God we ſhall do valiantly: for he it is that ſhall tread down our Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have divided my Text into Two Parts or Portions, like Two Regiments or Battalions of Soldiers, in which reſpect it repreſents
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35494:7"/>the Right and Left Wings of an Army. But having thus open'd my Text, both to the Right and Left, that I may put it again in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per form, I ſhall reduce the Diviſions as they were, and thereby bring it to its cloſe Order, drawing up the main Body thereof into a more Compleat and Warlike Poſture, by demonſtrating unto you in a conſiderable meaſure, what Glorious Conqueſts the Succeſsful and Succeſſive Sabaoths or Hoſts of God, obtain'd in former Ages over their Adverſaries: In order to which Demonſtration, I deſign thro' God's Gracious Aſſiſtance, to ſpeak unto the Two Chief Generals, or General Heads, poſted at the Royal Standard of my Text; as in the</p>
            <p>Firſt place, To King <hi>David</hi>'s Divine Conſideration, That the Foundation of a Juſt War in the Defence of his Peoples Lives, Laws, Liberties, and Religion, hath its Victorious Dependency on the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Power and Providence of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To King <hi>David</hi>'s Divine Suggeſtion, That tho' the People of God may be Inſtrumental in ſubduing their Enemies; yet the Succeſs that makes their Foes their Footſtool, is a principal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative only peculiar to God himſelf: Both which Obſervations are inſeparately included, and compleatly comprehended within the Bounds and Limits of my Celeſtial Subject, where in Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Aid from the Deity to ſuppreſs his Adverſaries; it is thus Dictated by Devout <hi>David, Through God we ſhall do valiantly: for he it is that ſhall tread down our Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all the Series of Holy Scripture, we may evidently behold, that when Almighty God intended to accompliſh ſome Notable Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to his People, he gave them to underſtand (in the mean ſpace) that it was not ſo much their own Might and Manhood, as it was his meer Mercy that ſaved them: And this is very Conſpicuous in the Couragious Reſolutions, and Admir'd Actions of the Religious <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites,</hi> who by their Military Affair, and God's Favour, overcame no leſs than Thirty One Conſiderable Kings and Kingdoms; as you may Read in the 12th Chapter of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> where there is a perfect Catalogue of their Names and Number; the firſt being the King of <hi>Jericho,</hi> mention'd in the 9th Verſe; and the laſt the King of <hi>Tirza,</hi> ſpecify'd in the 24th Verſe, which conſummates or concludes the ſame Chapter.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:35494:7"/>
            <p>Thus you ſee, according to the Words of my Text, how the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did valiantly; for God did tread down their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſrael,</hi> above all the Nations in the World, had the Honour of fighting the Lord's Battels; and when they wanted Champions or Conducts for their Encouragement, God was entreated by them, that his Power might appear in the cauſe of their Warfare: Who, according to his own good pleaſure, ſent ſeveral Reſcuers, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected them from Multitudes of malicious Enemies; one of whoſe Deliverers, or Saviour's, (as his Name imports it) was <hi>Joſhua</hi> the Son of <hi>Nun, Moſes</hi> his Miniſter and Succeſſor; for he deſtroy'd the <hi>Anakims</hi> in the Land of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> he alſo overcame many Prince's that reſiſted them, and hang'd five noted King's, on five ſeveral Trees, that were their Adverſaries; namely, <hi>Adoni-Zedeck</hi> King of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, Hoham</hi> King of <hi>Hebron, Piram</hi> King of <hi>Jarmuth, Japhia</hi> King of <hi>Lachiſh,</hi> and <hi>Debir</hi> King of <hi>Eglon,</hi> as you may read in the 9, 10, 11, and 12 Chapters of <hi>Joſhua.</hi> Thus <hi>Joſhua</hi> did valiantly; for God did tread down his Enemies.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were delivered from the bold Attempts of the <hi>Aramites,</hi> by <hi>Othniel</hi> the Son of <hi>Kenaz, Caleb</hi>'s younger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Land had reſt forty years, as it is obſervable <hi>Judg.</hi> 3.9, 10, 11. Thus <hi>Othniel</hi> did valiantly; for God did tread down his Enemies.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were preſerved from the Moleſtations of the <hi>Moabites,</hi> by <hi>Ehud</hi> the Son of <hi>Gera</hi> a <hi>Benjamite,</hi> a Man left-handed, when they ſlew of the Children of <hi>Moab</hi> about Ten thouſand Men, all luſty, all Men of Valour; ſo that the Land had reſt fourſcore years, as you may note in <hi>Judg.</hi> 3.15, 29, 30. Thus <hi>Ehud</hi> did valiantly; for God did tread down his Enemies.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were ſuccour'd from the Fury of <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines,</hi> by <hi>Shamgar</hi> the Son of <hi>Anath,</hi> who ſlew Six hundred <hi>Philiſtines</hi> with an Ox-goad; and he alſo delivered <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as it is apparent in <hi>Judg.</hi> 3.31. Thus <hi>Shamgar</hi> did valiantly; for God did tread down his Enemies.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:35494:8"/>
            <p>Fifthly, The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were deſended from the Incurſions of the <hi>Canaanites</hi> by <hi>Deborah</hi> a Propheteſs, the Wife of <hi>Lapidoth,</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rak</hi> the Son of <hi>Abinoam</hi> of <hi>Kadeſh-Nepthali,</hi> who by the aſſiſtance of God, prevailed againſt <hi>Jabin</hi> King of <hi>Canaan,</hi> until they had deſtroy'd <hi>Jabin</hi> King of <hi>Canaan;</hi> as is ſpecified in <hi>Judg.</hi> 4.6, 24. Thus <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borah</hi> and <hi>Barak</hi> did valiantly; for God did tread down their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were ſaved from the Miſchiefs of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianites</hi> by <hi>Jerubaal,</hi> that is, <hi>Gideon</hi> the Son of <hi>Joaſh</hi> the <hi>Abi-ezraite,</hi> who diſcomſited an Hoſt of Men with broken Potſherds, Lamps, and Rams-horns, together with the Noiſe of the People, who cried earneſtly before their Enemies, until they were daunted, routed, and ruined: <hi>The Sword of the Lord, and of Gideon,</hi> as it is recorded in <hi>Judges</hi> 7.20, 21. His Meſſenger alſo took two Princes of the <hi>Midia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, Oreb</hi> and <hi>Zeeb;</hi> and they ſlew <hi>Oreb</hi> upon the Rock <hi>Oreb,</hi> and <hi>Zeeb</hi> they ſlew at the Wine-preſs of <hi>Zeeb;</hi> and they purſued <hi>Midian,</hi> and brought the Heads of <hi>Oreb</hi> and <hi>Zeeb</hi> unto <hi>Gideon,</hi> on the other ſide <hi>Jordan,</hi> as it is remarkable in <hi>Judg.</hi> 7.24, 25. Alſo <hi>Gideon</hi> aroſe, and ſlew <hi>Zeba</hi> and <hi>Zalmunna,</hi> two chief Kings of <hi>Midian,</hi> as farther appears in <hi>Judg.</hi> 8.21. Thus <hi>Gideon</hi> did valiantly; for God did tread down his Enemies.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were protected from the Arms of the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> by <hi>Jepthah</hi> the <hi>Gileadite,</hi> a mighty Man of Valour, who ſmote the Children of <hi>Ammon</hi> from <hi>Aroer</hi> till thou come to <hi>Minnith,</hi> even twenty Cities; and unto the Plain of the Vineyards, with a very great Slaughter. Thus the Children of <hi>Ammon</hi> were ſubdu'd before the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as you may find it written in <hi>Judg.</hi> 11.33. Thus <hi>Jephthah</hi> did valiantly; for God did tread down his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were freed from the Forces of the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> by <hi>Samſon,</hi> who ſlew a Lion: He kill'd thirty <hi>Philiſtines</hi> for thirty Changes of Garments; burnt their Corn with Firebrands tied to three hundred Foxes Tails; carried away the Gates of <hi>Gaza;</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed a thouſand Men with the Jaw-bone of an Aſs; and by pulling upon him the Theatre of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> ſlew more at his death than he did in his life-time, as the Hiſtories thereof make mention, in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35494:8"/>14th, 15, and 16th Chapters of <hi>Judges.</hi> Thus <hi>Samſon</hi> did valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for God did tread down his Enemies.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were ſecur'd from the Onſets of the <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites, Moabites,</hi> and Inhabitants of <hi>Mount Seir,</hi> thro' the gracious and ſeaſonable Advice of good King <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> together with the Divine Aſſiſtance of Almighty God; as it is penn'd 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.20, 21, 22. where the Relation is thus worded: <hi>Here me, O Judah, and ye Inhabitants of Jeruſalem; believe in the Lord your God, ſo ſhall you be eſtabliſhed; believe his Prophets, ſo ſhall ye proſper. And when he had conſulted with the People, he appointed Singers unto the Lord, and that ſhould praiſe the Beauty of Holineſs, as they went out before the Army, and to ſay, Praiſe the Lord, for his Mercy endureth for ever. And when they began to ſing and to praiſe, the Lord ſet Ambuſhments againſt the Children of Ammon, Moab, and Mount Seir, which were come againſt Judah, and they were ſmitten,</hi> Thus <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> did valiantly; for God did tread down his Enemies. In the</p>
            <p>Tenth place, I ſhall, thro' God's Providential permiſſion, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate unto you ſome of the Noble Acts of Royal <hi>David,</hi> who (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Man after God's own Heart) always won the Field of the Lord's Battel under the Lord's Banner; according to theſe expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of my preſent Text: <hi>Through God we ſhall do valiantly; for he it is that ſhall tread down our Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We read in the Acts of renowned <hi>David,</hi> that when he was but a ruddy Youth, he kill'd a Lion and a Bear, as alſo ſlew the Chief Champion of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> namely, the Great <hi>Goliah</hi> of <hi>Gath;</hi> as you may read in the 17th Chapter of the Firſt Book of <hi>Samuel.</hi> He ſmote two hundred <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> for which Exploit he had the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Majeſtical Aſſinity, in being made the King's Son-in-Law, as appears in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. He took a Spear, and a Pot or Cruiſe of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that ſtood at <hi>Saul</hi>'s head, as you may note in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26. He warred the Lord's Warfare, and ſlew <hi>Rechab,</hi> and <hi>Baana</hi> his Brother, the Sons of <hi>Rimmon</hi> the <hi>Beerothite,</hi> as you have it obſervable in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. He overcame the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> twice; he took the Fort <hi>Sion;</hi> he reſtored the Ark; he prepar'd for the Building of the Temple he overthrew the <hi>Aramites,</hi> and all his Enemies, as you may far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remark in the 5th and 6th Chapters of the Second Book of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel.</hi> Thus, according to the words of my Text, <hi>David</hi> the Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35494:9"/>of God did valiantly; for He did tread down his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome of the Royal Prophet's Atchievements, who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch Undertakings always conſided in God's willingneſs and readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to aſſiſt his Endeavours, in all neceſſary Engagements: For the Lord himſelf, who is a Man of War, veſted him in an heavenly and impenetrable Coat of Mail, or ſpiritual Armour, according to thoſe prudent and prevalent Expreſſions, of his unbyaſs'd Reſolution and Reliance, recorded <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.1, 2, 3. where he thus expoſtulated with himſelf, touching his holy Warfare: <hi>The Lord is my Light and my Salvation; whom ſhall I fear? The Lord is the Strength of my Life; of whom ſhall I be afraid? When the Wicked, even mine Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and my Foes came upon me to eat up my Fleſh, they ſtumbled and fell. Tho' an Hoſt ſhould encamp againſt me, my Heart ſhall not fear: Tho' War ſhould riſe againſt me, in this will I be conſident.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ought to be the couragious Reſolution of all ſincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, but more eſpecially of Chriſtian Soldiers, who ſeem to carry their Lives in their Hands, and are obſerved to ſtand upon the brink of the Grave: Yet if ſuch conſide with <hi>David,</hi> in the corroborating Power of God, taking cognizance of the Equity of our late conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued War, and the juſt demerit of the Cauſe thereof, being in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Chriſt's Goſpel, and ſuch Kingdoms, Territories, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and Provinces, as maintain his true Religion, together with the Lives, Laws, and Liberties of free-born Subjects, who are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by protected from infringing their Priviledges, invading their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, and infecting the Principles of their pious Profeſſion: Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſuch neceſſary Warriors may have a welcom Acceſs to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of my preſent Text, in order to defend God's Word with <hi>David</hi>'s Sword, and there to ſay with the ſacred Pſalmiſt: <hi>Through God we ſhall do valiantly; for he it is that ſhall tread down our Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this place, I have form'd or fram'd my Text, to bear a lively Repreſentation of the late Aſſairs of our <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Nation; where a Party of its Inhabitants, like the diſturb'd <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> have had ſeveral Commotions both with domeſtick and foreign Enemies: This Truth is experimentally memoriz'd by many of us, who, through God's gracious permiſſion, have our continuance hitherto in the Land of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35494:9"/>living. But what ſhall we ſay to theſe things? ſince God hath been for us, who could be againſt us? For <hi>through God we have done va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly; he trod down theſe our Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was the good Pleaſure of God Almighty, in ſundry, and ſome late years paſt, to ſend variety of Judgments upon the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> that the Inhabitants thereof might learn Righteouſneſs; as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Chap.</hi> 26.9. But as the pious Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſaith, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 28.5. we have not regarded the Works of the Lord, nor the operation of his Hands, either in the late noiſom Peſtilence which ſwept away thouſands (in the Metropolitan City of the ſaid Realm, namely, <hi>London</hi>) hurrying them into the dark and gloomy Chambers of the Grave; nor the raging Fire, which burnt up the Dwellings of many thouſand Families, burying them in their own Ruins; nor the revenging Sword, that in the Series of War ſlew a marvelous multitude of our Martial Men, in their Engagements with furious Enemies: And becauſe we are not yet reclaim'd by all theſe ſignal and ſingular Tokens of God's Diſpleaſure with us, we may juſtly fear, that Providence prepares ſome other ſeverer Judgment, either utterly to deſtroy us from off the face of the Earth, or to force us in it unto better Obedience. And to this purpoſe are thoſe terrible Threatnings of a rewarding God, recorded in <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.15, 16, 17, 18. where he ſpeaks theſe dreadful Expreſſions: <hi>If ye ſhall deſpiſe my Statutes, or if your Soul ſhall abhor my Judgments, ſo that you will not do all my Commandments, but that ye break my Covenant: I alſo will do this unto you; I will even appoint over you Terrour, Conſumption, and the burning Ague, that ſhall conſume the Eyes, and cauſe ſorrow of Heart: And ye ſhall ſow your Seed in vain, for your Enemies ſhall eat it. And I will ſet my face againſt you, and ye ſhall be ſlain before your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. They that hate you, ſhall reign over you, and ye ſhall flee when none purſueth you. And if ye will not yet for all this hearken unto me, then will I puniſh you ſeven times more for your ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we have a ſatisfactory Account, in what way or method God uſually proceeds to inflict his Wrath upon refractory Sinners: Firſt, he impoſeth one Calamity; and if that reclaim them not, then he will add a ſecond, ſometimes doubling that with a fourth, or trebbling it with the ſixth Affliction. And if all theſe work not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hardneſs of their Hearts, then will he prepare another, that like <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s Fiery Furnace, ſhall be ſeven times more pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35494:10"/>than the former. Moreover, it is the Cuſtomary Phraſe of God in Scripture, when his Holineſs would deter us from Vice, to threaten our Deſtruction with Vengeance, as in <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.35. where he ſaith, <hi>To me belongeth Vengeance and Recompence.</hi> Again, he ſpeaks in Ver. 41. of the ſame Chapter, <hi>If I whet my glittering Sword, and mine Hand take hold on Judgment, I will render Vengeance to mine Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and will Reward them that hate me.</hi> And in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 25.17. thus ſaith the Lord concerning the Deſtruction of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> and <hi>Cherethims, I will execute great Vengeance upon them with furious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes; and they ſhall know that I am the Lord, when I ſhall lay my Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it is obſervable, that as the heavy Judgments of God are made ſo unconceivably intolerable, by the weight of Divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, our ſafeſt Courſe in avoiding of them, is to flee from Sin to his Sanctuary, and there humbly and devoutly pray for the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for they ſhall all proſper that love Communion with the Church of God; and that your Requeſts may be made conformable to God's moſt holy Will, at all times, in all places, and upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, both Chriſt and his Church to that end have furniſh'd you with ſufficient Rules of Devotion, he in the form of his gracious Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, and ſhe in the frame of her Pious Ejaculations: He in his Petitions ſaying, <hi>Lead us not into Temptations but deliver us from Evil;</hi> and ſhe in her Alluſive Ejaculations ſaying, <hi>From all Evil and Miſchief, from Sin, from the Craſts and Aſſaults of the Devil, from thy Wrath, and from Everlaſting Damnation, good Lord deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many Material Circumſtances might be alledg'd to demonſtrate our Church and its Government conſiſtent with the Divine Will and Pleaſure of God, for ſhe is ſo highly in Favour with the Higheſt, that he remov'd thoſe who caus'd her Breaches, far from her, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to uphold her Walls and Bulwarks; yea, her Intereſt appears ſo Intereſted in God, that he lately Dethron'd a King that offended her, and in his ſtead, Enthron'd a King to defend her. <hi>This is the Lord's doing, it is Marvellous in our Eyes;</hi> as the Kingly Prophet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth it in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.23. <hi>For Promotion cometh neither from the Eaſt, nor from the Weſt, nor from the South. But God is the Judge: He putteth down one, and ſetteth up another,</hi> as appears, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.6, 7. That this Dethronement and Eſtabliſhment was God's own Handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work, is Divinely Vindicated by the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35494:10"/>Caſe; and Preternatural Condition of King <hi>Nebuchadnezzar;</hi> who for his unſufferable Arrogance, was Exil'd from the Society of Rational Men, to take his Abode and Food with the unreaſonable Beaſts of the Field; touching whom the ſaid <hi>Daniel</hi> in his ſecond Chapter at the 20th and 21th Verſes, ſpake on this Wiſe, <hi>Bleſſed be the Name of God for ever and ever: for Wiſdom and Might are his. And he changeth the Times, and the Seaſons: He removeth Kings, and ſetteth up Kings: He giveth Wiſdom unto the Wiſe, and Knowledge to them that know <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi> Again, we Read in the 37th Verſe of the ſame Chapter, that the Prophet ſaid to the King on this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>Thou, O King, art a King of Kings; for the God of Heaven hath given thee a Kingdom, Power, and Strength, and Glory.</hi> Moreover <hi>Daniel</hi> told him in the 4th Chapter of his Propheſie at the 25th Verſe, <hi>That the moſt High ruleth in the Kingdom of Men, and giveth it to whomſoever he will.</hi> Thus we ſee that the diſpoſal of Earthly Kingdoms, is a peculiar Prerogative abſolutely pertaining to the King of Heaven; for God being an Univerſal Monarch, hath agene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Title attributed unto him, in <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.7. where he is ſtil'd by the Prophet, <hi>The King of Nations.</hi> And that becauſe all Emperors, Kings, and Princes, in their Enthronements, wear their Crowns, ſway their Scepters. govern their Kingdoms and Principalities, by God's own ſpecial Authority: This Truth bears the Badge of his warrantable and undoubted Teſtification, in the 8th Chapter of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>'s <hi>Proverbs,</hi> Ver. 15. where he ſpeaks theſe certain and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Expreſſions, <hi>By me Kings Reign, and Princes Decree Juſtice.</hi> This Aſſirmation hath ſufficient Aſſertions of Scripture to aſſure it, as in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12 7. where God by the Mouth of his Prophet <hi>Nathan,</hi> ſpake theſe words unto <hi>David, I anointed thee King over</hi> Iſrael: <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> alſo acknowledg'd, that <hi>the Lord had plac'd and eſtabliſh'd him on the Throne of his Father</hi> David, as you may Read in 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.24. Moreover it was the ſaying of <hi>Ahijah</hi> in the Perſon of God to <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam, I will give the Kingdom unto thee;</hi> as it is obſervable in 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.35. By all theſe Scripture Inſtances it plainly and punctually ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the removing and ſetling of Crown'd Heads, relate to God's Diſpenſative Power; and therefore we may ſay of God in ſuch Caſes, as <hi>Job</hi> ſpake concerning the Life and Death of his Children, in, <hi>Job</hi> 1.21. <hi>The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away, bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi> Having thus prov'd unto you, that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of this Lower World, is according to the Rule of God's undeniable and unlimitted Authority; ſo neither the Kingdoms, nor
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35494:11"/>Power of Princes, but all things elſe proper unto them, are after a peculiar manner God's, their Crowns, their Anointing, their Globes, their Scepters, their Thrones, and the Government there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are his; and their Perſons adorn'd with all theſe Endowments, are ſo Sublime and Sacred, that they are compar'd for Excellent Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, or Eminent Excellency, unto the Angels of God, in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.17. and alſo ſtil'd Gods, by a Deify'd kind of Dignity, and call'd the Children of the moſt High, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6.</p>
            <p>From theſe and ſuch like Obſervations, the ſanctify'd Veſſel St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that great Apoſtle and Patron of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> compil'd an Excellent Lecture of Loyalty, in order to oblige both Religious and Rebellious Subjects, to bear true Allegiance and ſubmiſſive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence unto their Supream and Lawful Superiors; the which you may find Recorded in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2. where it is thus worded, <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject unto the Higher Powers; for there is no Power, but of God. The Powers that be are ordained of God. Whoſoever therefore reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God; and they that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi> Hence it is obſervable, that as every individual Perſon ought to be in ſubjection to his ſuperior and inferior Rulers, by reaſon that the Power of their Government is derivative from God, and the Governours now in being, Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by his Ordinance, whom to reſiſt, is plain oppoſition to God's own Order, for which reſiſtance they become liable to receive unto themſelves the Reward or Stipend of Damnation. Therefore to abandon Diſloyalty, being the Cauſe of this Damnable Alot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as Religious Servants to God, Loyal Subjects to the King, and Loving Sons of the Church: Let us that are her Empal'd Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren firmly ſtand in God's, the King's, and the Church her Cauſe, reſolving, that in caſe no other Kingdom or Nation, ſhould accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate us with their Aſſiſtance, neither to dread, nor to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may'd at it, although our preſent Enemies, whomſoever they are, may ſeem much more in number than our ſelves, for the Race is not always to the ſwift, nor the Battel ſtill to the ſtrong, but to thoſe that have God for their powerful Copartner; for there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint to the Lord, to ſave by many or by few, as it is obſervable in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.6. This Truth is farther confirm'd by the Divine Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of <hi>Aſa,</hi> who with an Army of Five Hundred and Fourſcore Thouſand Men, waged War with <hi>Zerah</hi> the <hi>Ethiopian,</hi> whoſe Hoſt conſiſted of a Thouſand Thouſand in number, as you may note in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35494:11"/>2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14.8, 9, 10. Moreover it is ſaid in Verſe 11. <hi>That</hi> Aſa <hi>cryed unto the Lord his God, and ſaid, Lord, it is nothing with thee to help, whether with many, or with them that have no Power: Help us, O Lord our God; for we reſt on thee, and in thy Name we go againſt this multitude; ſo the Lord ſmote the</hi> Ethiopians <hi>before</hi> Aſa, <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> Judah, as you may Read in Verſe 12. of the ſame Chapter: Theſe Excellent Obſervations have their full and clear Evidence in <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.1, 2, 3, 4. where God granted unto <hi>Iſrael</hi> a Warlike Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion Seal'd with his own Hand, and deliver'd with his own Mouth, in theſe Expreſſions Recorded by <hi>Moſes, When thou goeſt to Battel againſt thine Enemies, and ſeeſt Horſes and Chariots, and a People more than thou, be not afraid of them; for the Lord thy God is with thee, which brought thee up out of the Land of</hi> Egypt. <hi>And it ſhall be when ye are come nigh unto the Battel, that the Prieſt ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and ſpeak unto the People, and ſhall ſay unto them, Hear, O</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, <hi>you approach this day unto Battel againſt your Enemies; let not your Hearts faint, fear not, and do not tremble, neither be ye terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied becauſe of them; for the Lord your God is he that goeth with you, to fight for you againſt your Enemies, to ſave you.</hi> In this Divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, we have a Reviving Cordial to cheer up the drooping Spirits of a faint-hearted Soldier; for it is matter of no great moment to him whether his Enemies are many or mighty, ſince he hath the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Promiſe of the moſt Mighty to take his part in all Lawful En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements; then a Thouſand may fall at his ſide, and Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand at his Right Hand, but it ſhall not come nigh him. God will be with him in Trouble, to deliver him, and honour him. With long Life alſo will he ſatisfie him, and ſhew him his Salvation, as it is expreſt in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.7, 15, 16. Therefore for ſuch a Deliverance as is here promis'd, let us give unto the Lord the Glory due unto his Name; for God is never more pleas'd with us, than when his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Maieſty is moſt prais'd by us: A frequent Acknowledgment of God's Praiſes, is an undeniable means of obtaining our deſir'd Deliverances: And to this end, becauſe our frail Lives are uncertain, by reaſon of Deſtructive Wars, with other daily Caſualties; and that while we have our continuance on this ſide the Grave, we may live in God's fear, and in our departure hence, Die in his Favour, thereby to obtain Eternal Felicity. I humbly crave your Chriſtian Patience for ſome few Moments, that I may diſcover unto you what Praiſe is, together with the Fruits and Effects of it in Ten brief Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35494:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>alſo how God is to be praiſed, in Six Compendious Points.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, Praiſe is the End, or Ultimate part of our Devout Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions; for we call upon, and importune God to beſtow on us out of the Rich Treaſury of his Bounty, and unexhauſted Supplies, ſuch Benefits as are moſt neceſſary or needful, both for our Corporal and Spiritual Neceſſities, that we may bleſs and praiſe him for the ſame; to which purpoſe Holy <hi>David</hi> in 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.35. teacheth us a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Method how to ſweeten our Prayers with Praiſes, according to theſe Expreſſions, <hi>Save us, O God of our Salvation, and deliver us, that we may give thanks to thy Holy Name, and Glory in thy Praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Praiſe maketh Petition powerful, for God is moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and willing to hear their Petitions, whoſe Hearts are inclinable to praiſe him, in giving due Thanks for former Benefits, we do as it were engage God thereby, to confer upon us further or future Bleſſings. For on this Direction of <hi>David</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.14. <hi>Offer unto God Thankſgiving,</hi> the Lord himſelf made this Gracious Promiſe in the next Verſe, <hi>Call upon me in the day of Trouble, I will deliver thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Praiſe is a due Debt, which Petitioners are bound to pay; for he that inviteth thee to call upon him, and promiſeth thy Deliverance from Trouble, requireth and expecteth that Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation or Recompence from thee, as to Reward his Promiſe with thy Praiſe, according to theſe Expreſſions of deſerv'd Retaliation, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. <hi>Thou ſhalt glorifie me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Praiſe is the full Requital that we can give unto God for every good and perfect Gift, which his Divine Benignity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth upon us; for when the praying and praiſing Pſalmiſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded this Queſtion in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.12. <hi>What ſhall I render unto the Lord, for all his Benefits towards me?</hi> The Anſwer or Reſolution was thus given in Ver. 13. <hi>I will take the Cup of Salvation, and call upon the Name of the Lord:</hi> As if <hi>David</hi> ſhould have ſaid, I will offer a ſolemn Sacrifice, wherewith, wherein, or whereby I may clearly manifeſt the numerous and tremendous Deliverances or Preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which God hath afforded to me; for by way of Expoſition, he addeth theſe words in Ver. 17. of the ſame <hi>Pſalm, I will offer to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35494:12"/>thee the Sacrifice of Thankſgiving, and will call upon the Name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, Praiſe is a Satisfactory Evidence of that good Reſpect which we owe to the Lord our God. By Petition, we ſhow that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour which we bear towards our ſelves. The Ten Lepers who came unto Chriſt, lifting up their Voices, and ſaying, <hi>Jeſus, Maſter have Mercy on us, Luke</hi> 17.13. ſhew'd a care of their own welfare, only one who return'd to give Glory unto God, diſcover'd his Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of the Lord's Honour.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Praiſe is ſo prevalent a Duty, that it moves God to ſhew good Eſtimation or Reſpect to Men; for he that ſaid in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. <hi>Them that honour me, will I honour,</hi> without Controverſie will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form ſo punctual a Promiſe.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Praiſe is the greateſt Honour that we can give to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, for it is his own Declaration or Acknowledgment, in reference to his Divine and Eſſential Fame, Recorded in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.23. <hi>He that offereth Praiſe, glorifieth me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eightly, To Praiſe God, is the moſt Excellent Piece of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Service that in this World can be perform'd; and alſo all the Celeſtial Spirits are concern'd herein, as it is obſervable in <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.13. where he ſaith, <hi>That every Creature which is in Heaven, and on the Earth, and under the Earth, and ſuch as are in the Sea, and all that are in them, heard I, ſaying, Bleſſing, Honour, Glory and Power be unto him that ſitteth upon the Throne, and unto the Lamb for Ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ninthly, A ſetting forth of God's Praiſe, is an indubitable means to enliven the Spirit, and to make the Heart of Man more ready, active, and chearful in performing the Duty of Prayer; for when <hi>David</hi>'s Heart was in a prepar'd Temper to praiſe God, he preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applies himſelf thereto, and by confeſſing his ſtability therein, ſaid to his Tuneable Tongue, and Muſical Inſtruments, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.7, 8. 9. <hi>My Heart is ſixed, O God, my Heart is fixed: I will ſing and give praiſe. Awake up my Glory, awake Pſaltery and Harp, I my ſelf will awake early. I will praiſe thee, O Lord, among the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, I will ſing unto thee among the Nations.</hi> When the Spirit of a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35494:13"/>Man is under an undiſpoſedneſs to pray, let him then meditate on the Mercies and Excellencies of God, by which Divine Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he ſhall find a Spiritual Vivification and Vigour put into him.</p>
            <p>Tenthly and Laſtly, Praiſe is comely or pleaſant, as Devout <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> phraſes it in his acceptable <hi>Pſalms</hi> of Thankſgiving; but Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude is one of the moſt odious and vicious Qualities that can be nam'd, for <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s ungratefulneſs or unthankfulneſs was the only Cauſe of their Captivity, as you may Read in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.16, 17. where part of the Hiſtory is thus related, <hi>They mocked the Meſſengers of God, and deſpiſed his words, and miſuſed his Prophets, until the Wrath of the Lord aroſe againſt his People, till there was no Remedy. Therefore he brought upon them the King of the</hi> Chaldees, <hi>who ſlew their young Men with the Sword, in the Houſe of their Sanctuary, and had no Compaſſion upon young Man or Maiden, old Man, or him that ſtooped for Age; he gave them all into his Hand.</hi> We find that unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was the main Reaſon why God gave the <hi>Gentiles</hi> over to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate Sence, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21. and Chriſtians over to Antichriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, as you may note in 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.9, 10, 11, 12. This alſo caus'd that <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was transform'd into the Nature of a Beaſt, as you may Read in <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.20, 21. And that <hi>Herod</hi> was eaten up of Worms, as it is Recorded in <hi>Acts</hi> 12.23. Therefore let us learn from their harms to beware of Ingratitude, and even at this preſent inſtant, or juncture of time, return Thanks unto God for thoſe great Deliverances and manifold Mercies, which we continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Enjoy'd from the Moment of our Nativity, to this preſent Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, reſolving from henceforth (until our departure out of this Life) to render Praiſe unto him for whatſoever Benefits or Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings his good Providence may treaſure up for us in order to our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Happineſs; ſaying with the Sacred Pſalmiſt in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.18, 19. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God, the God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>who only doth wondrous things. And bleſſed be his glorious Name for ever, and let the whole Earth be filled with his Glory, Amen, and Amen.</hi> Thus have I ſhew'd you what Praiſe is, together with the Fruits and Effects of it in Ten Particulars.</p>
            <p>In the next place, I deſign by God's permiſſion to demonſtrate unto you how God is to be praiſed, and that in theſe Six Compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Points.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:35494:13"/>
            <p>Firſt of all, God is praiſed by acknowledging him to be what he is, in Himſelf, in his Son, in his Spirit, in his Properties, and in his Attributes: For <hi>Moſes,</hi> in his Pſalm of Thankſgiving, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.3. did praiſe God by ſpeaking of him on this wiſe: <hi>The Lord is a Man of War; The Lord is his Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, God is praiſed by attributing unto him that which is his, as holy <hi>David</hi> did, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.10, 11, 12, 13. where it is thus written: <hi>Wherefore</hi> David <hi>bleſſed the Lord before all the Congregation: And</hi> David <hi>ſaid, Bleſſed be thou, Lord God of</hi> Iſrael <hi>our Father, for ever and ever. Thine, O Lord, is the Greatneſs, and the Power, and the Glory, and the Victory, and the Majeſty; for all that is in the Heaven and the Earth is thine; thine is the Kingdom, O Lord, and thou art ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted as Head above all. Both Riches and Honour come of thee, and thou reigneſt over all, and in thine hand is Power and Might, and in thine hand it is to make great, and to give strength unto all. Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, our God, we thank thee, and praiſe thy Holy Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, God is praiſed, by acknowledging that which his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſeemingly effects, to be only done or perform'd by himſelf. Thus doth <hi>Moſes</hi> praiſe God, by aſcribing unto him the Overthrow of <hi>Pharoah</hi> and his Hoſts in the Red Sea, as you may obſerve <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.4. So alſo doth the Pſalmiſt, in moſt of his Pſalms of Praiſe; as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.1. and from the 15th Verſe to the 23d. where it is thus worded: <hi>O give thanks unto the Lord, for he is good; for his Mercy endureth for ever. To him that overthrew</hi> Pharach <hi>and his Hoſt in the Red Sea: To him which led his People through the Wilderneſs: To him which ſmote great Kings, and ſlew famous Kings;</hi> Sihon <hi>King of the</hi> Amorites, <hi>and</hi> Og <hi>the King of</hi> Baſhan; <hi>and gave their Land for an Heritage; even an Heritage unto</hi> Iſrael <hi>his Servant: And this he did, becauſe his Mercy to his People endureth for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, God is praiſed by owning that which he diſpoſeth, to be only given of himſelf; this was <hi>David</hi>'s candid acknowledgment of God's hounteous Benefits and liberal Gifts, in 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.14. where he thus ſpake unto the Lord: <hi>All things come of thee, and of thine own have we given thee.</hi> Alſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36. <hi>Of him, and through him, and to him are all things; to whom be Glory for ever. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:35494:14"/>
            <p>Fifthly, God is praiſed by declaring or mentioning unto others all the fore-named Points concerning him. Thus did the ſweet-tongu'd <hi>David,</hi> that ſingular Singer of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.8, 9. where he ſpeaks theſe godly Expreſſions: <hi>Give unto the Lord the glory due unto his Name; bring an Offering, and come before him: Worſhip the Lord in the Beauty of Holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus alſo have I ſhow'd you, in ſix compendious Points, how God is to be praiſed.</p>
            <p>If therefore, according to theſe pithy and practical Points of Piety, our Hearts are inclinable to praiſe God, who is the moſt Victorious Conqueror and matchleſs Man of War, under whoſe Bellonick or Warlike Banner, we ſeem terrible in ſight of our Adverſaries; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, as <hi>Abijah</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.12. That God Himſelf is with us for our Captain, triumphing gloriouſly for the Diſcomfiture and Deſtruction of his Peoples Enemies: As <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaks concerning the Overthrow of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> in <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.4. and of whom <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 98.1. That he hath done miraculous things; for nis right Hand, and his holy Arm hath gotten him the Victory: That by this means (as <hi>Zacharias</hi> propheſied of Chriſt and his believing People, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.74, 75.) <hi>We being delivered out of the hands of our Enemies, might ſerve him without fear, in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs before him all the days of our life;</hi> renewing the Vow and Covenant that we made with Chriſt in our Baptiſm, of fighting manfully under his Banner againſt Sin, the World, and the Devil; and to continue his faithful Soldiers and Servants unto our Lives end: To which end, in order to prolong our Lives and ſee good Days, by keeping our Tongues from Evil, and Lips from guile, we muſt aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and abominate all horrid and raſh Jurations, all haſty and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Proteſtations, all helliſh and heinous Imprecations, all envious and evil Communications, with all unchaſte Deſires and uncivil De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment in our Lives and Chriſtian Converſations; for in ſo doing, we have God's own inviolable Promiſes, to be ſtill aiding or aſſiſting to us, in all Manly and Military Enterprizes. So that we may well agree in the pious Opinion and divine Diſpoſition of indubitable and undaunted <hi>David,</hi> to ſay in the Dialect or Warlike Words of my Text: <hi>Through God we ſhall do valiantly; for he it is that ſhall tread down our Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:35494:14"/>
            <p>This Portion of Scripture, is a Text befitting the holy Parade and Camp of the Lord of Hoſts; for we have God in the Front, God in the Center, and God in the Reer of it: If we wheel the Text to the Right hand, there we ſhall find God triumphing; if to the Right about, there triumphing valiantly; if we move the Text to the Left hand, there we ſhall find God trampling; if to the Left about, there trampling down our Enemies: If we place the Words as they were, either upon their orderly Guard, or in their cloſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and as on the Patrol, walk the Rounds of my Text, <hi>Through God we ſhall do valiantly; for he it is that ſhall tread down our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus rendezvous'd, countermarch'd, exercis'd, or muſter'd my Text, and form'd the Bands, Battalions, and Squadrons of our Camp in Battel Array, let us proceed in the Name of the Lord of Hoſts, to diſplay unto our Enemies the Flag of Defiance, and make our Proclamation with holy <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 18.1, 2, 3. ſaying on this wiſe: <hi>We will love thee, O Lord our Strength: The Lord is our Rock, and our Fortreſs, and our Deliverer: Our God, our Strength, in whom we will truſt; our Buckler, and the Horn of our Salvation, and our high Tower. We will call upon the Lord, who is worthy to be praiſed; ſo ſhall we be ſaved from our Enemies.</hi> Like to this cordial and cheerful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, was that comfortable Speech which good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> made to enliven and encourage his Army, who being but few in number, as compared with their Enemies, the great Hoſt of <hi>Senacherib</hi> King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> were nevertheleſs, by a ſetled Dependence on God's Power, both willing and ready to give them the Encounter, as you may read in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.7, 8. where it is thus related: <hi>Be ſtrong and couragious, be not afraid nor diſmayed for the King of</hi> Aſſyria, <hi>nor for all the Multitude that is with him; for there be more with us than with him: With him is an Arm of Fleſh, but with us is the Lord our God, to help us and to ſight our Battels. And the People reſted themſelves upon the Words of</hi> Hezekiah <hi>King of</hi> Judah: <hi>And while the People reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Words of</hi> Hezekiah, <hi>behold the Lord ſent a deſtroying An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, that on the ſame night ſmote in the Camp of the Alliances, an hundred and fourſcore and five thouſand. And when the People roſe up early in the Morning, behold they were all dead Corpſes,</hi> as you may read <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the 2d of the <hi>Kings,</hi> Chap. 19. Verſ. 35.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:35494:15"/>
            <p>Hence we may obſerve, that a King who had the beſt Cauſe, never fail'd of the beſt Courage: The ſame may be ſaid of <hi>WILLIAM</hi> the Third, King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> for God hath given him a good Cauſe of War againſt his Enemies, as, namely, the ſecuring of pure Religion, the procuring of laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Peace, the uniting of divided Kingdoms, the compoſing of Peoples Differences, the preſerving of wholeſom Laws, the correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of diſloyal Servants, and the protecting of Loyal Subjects. Theſe being the Cauſes of God, the King, and the Church, do ſo enhance his Majeſty's Spirit, that he is not afraid to meet his Enemies in the Gate, but ſeems to declare his Intereſt in the Lord, with holy <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 118.6, 7. where the Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal King ſpeaks on this wiſe: <hi>The Lord is on my ſide, I will not fear what Man can do unto me: The Lord taketh my part with them that help me; therefore ſhall I ſee my deſire upon them that hate me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence we may find it obſervable, that the Lord alſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth part with our King's Party, in order to fulfil his Deſire upon his Enemies. This Truth viſibly appears in the late Wars that were managed both in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories of <hi>Flanders,</hi> where God wonderfully preſerv'd his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Sacred Perſon from the violent and revenging Peril of the Sword; as if no Weapon form'd againſt him ſhould proſper; like one intereſted in thoſe Eſcapes of <hi>David,</hi> mentioned <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. v. 50. namely, <hi>Great Deliverances giveth he to his King, and ſheweth Mercy to his Anointed, to</hi> David <hi>and to his Seed</hi> (and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Succeſſors) <hi>for evermore.</hi> Many miraculous Deliverances hath his Majeſty already experienc'd, as if a Guardian or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camping Angel, had a ſpecial Commiſſion from Heaven, at all times, in all places, and upon all occaſions, to protect or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his pious Perſon. Such a Commiſſionated-Angel we read of in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. verſ. 7. where it is ſaid, That <hi>the Angel of the Lord encampeth round about them that fear him, and delivereth them.</hi> But of all the miraculous Deliverances and Preſervations which Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven decreed for his Safety, the moſt capital and remarkable was his laſt Eſcape from a curſed Cabal of Aſſaſſinates, who by miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Machinations, hatch'd a Helliſh Stratagem how to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35494:15"/>their hateful and unhallow'd Hands in the ſcarlet and crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Dyes of his Royal Blood, had not God (as the Anointed of Himſelf) prevented the Martyrdom by a matchleſs Miracle of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious Mercy.</p>
            <p>We have not, beſides what Divine Revelation affords, a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Argument to prove this World to be govern'd, and all Things in it, carried on and directed by the vigilant Eye and powerful Hand of Almighty GOD, than the ſudden and ſeaſonable Diſcoveries of ſuch damnable Enterprizes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd with the utmoſt Caution and Secreſie; propagated with great Subtilty or Cunning, and being juſt ripe for execution; yet in an inſtant blaſted, in a trice broken all to pieces, either by a ſurprizing dread ſeizing the Conſpirators themſelves, or an unwary Word over-heard, or an unaccountable Suſpicion of ill Deſigns, though founded upon no reaſon, or a very trifling one, yet hath proved true; or God ſmote upon the Conſcience of ſome one of them, and for the eaſe of his tortur'd Mind, he is forced to a Diſcovery.</p>
            <p>Peradventure their Jealouſie of being betray'd by others, hath made ſome to give notice of it themſelves. A Letter miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd, a Fright, Miſtake, Overſight, or ſomething happening otherwiſe than was expected, hath brought the hidden Works of Darkneſs to light, whereby the King and his Liege People, or Loyal Subjects, have been mercifully ſnatch'd from the Jaws of Ruin, and the Conſpirators themſelves brought to condign Puniſhment, according to that remarkable Obſervation of the Royal Prophet, in his IX. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> at the 16th. Verſe; where he ſaith,</p>
            <p>That <hi>the Lord is known by the Judgment which he executeth: The Wicked is ſnared in the Work of his own Hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:35494:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>From theſe Diabolical and Inhumane Attempts, may the Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcient, Omnipreſent, and Omnipotent God, Protect His Majeſties Gracious Perſon, to improve that prepar'd Portion which we hope Divine Providence hath laid up for him in the Diſpoſal of Sacred Providence, as <hi>length of Days in her Right Hand, and in her Left Hand Riches and Honour. For her Ways are Ways of Pleaſantneſs, and all her Paths are Peace,</hi> as appears in <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.16, 17. Seeing therefore that the plain Paths of Wiſdom are all of them both pleaſant and peaceable, let us learn of her to be ſo prudent as to make our Addreſſes unto God, that he would be pleas'd to withdraw our Feet from the rugged Ways of War and Bloodſhed, that he may guide them into the ſmooth and pleaſant Paths of Peace; for in ſo doing, both Church and State will famouſly ſlouriſh. This was a Pious and a Primitive Obſervation among the <hi>Jews,</hi> as appears in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.1, 2, 3. where holy <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks theſe Expreſſions, <hi>In</hi> Judah <hi>is God known: his Name is great in</hi> Iſrael. <hi>In</hi> Salem <hi>alſo is his Tabernacle, and his Dwelling-place in</hi> Sion. <hi>There brake he the Arrows of the Bow, the Shield, and the Sword, and the Battel.</hi> But now to the Praiſe and Glory of God, we Chriſtians may ſay, That in <hi>Britain</hi> is God known, his Name is great in <hi>England,</hi> in the <hi>Salem</hi> of our <hi>Britiſh</hi> Dominion is his Tabernacle, and his Dwelling-place in the <hi>Sion</hi> of our Three Kingdoms. There alſo brake he the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of the Bow, the Shield, and the Sword, and the Battel, where the Church of God hath a ſound Principled King to her Nurſing-father, Elected and Eſtabliſhed by Divine Providence, to Defend her from Wrong and Violence; and tho' her furious Foes are many, yet her Faithful Friend is Mighty, for God is in the midſt of her, therefore ſhe ſhall not be moved; God ſhall help her, and that right early, as holy <hi>David</hi> well obſerves in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.5. Since therefore that God is a very preſent help in, Trouble unto his Militant or Warfaring Church, we are in that reſpect oblig'd to pray unto him for her good Succeſs and Proſperity, as that his Divine Pleaſure might be intreated to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn and continue her in the Beautiful Ornaments of Unity, Peace, and Concord; for in her Peace we ſhall enjoy Peace. It is a certain Truth, that as War is the Producer of Mortality, Poverty, and Perplexity among Men, in that Kingdom or Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wherein it is ſeated; ſo Peace is the Procurer of Safety, Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35494:16"/>and Proſperity, both to Church and State; for which cauſe the Sacred Pſalmiſt exhorted and excited the People (in his time) to Pray for the Peace of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, which Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are very ſuitable and uſeful for the Church of God under Chriſtianity, as appears in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.6, 7, 8, 9. where the ſweet Singer, and Orator of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> thus ſpake unto his Fellow-peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, <hi>Pray for the Peace of</hi> Jeruſalem: <hi>They ſhall proſper that love thee. Peace be within thy Walls, and Proſperity within thy Palaces. For my Brethren and Companions ſakes, I will now ſay, Peace be within thee. Becauſe of the Houſe of the Lord our God, I will ſeek thy good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next to our Petitions for the Peace of the Church, we ought to Pray for the Peace and Proſperity of the King, that God would be pleas'd to endue him with a Long Life, a Proſperous Reign, a Secure State and Habitation, Unbyaſs'd Repreſentatives, a Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Privy-Council and Parliament, Judicious and Conſciencious Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, Mild and Merciful Magiſtrates, Able and Valuable Phyſicians, a Plentiful and Painful Miniſtry, a Victorious Fleet and Army, and all ſorts of his Subjects that are Profeſſors of Arts, Sciences, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther National Occupations, a Religious, Loving, and a Loyal Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; all which will very much tend to advance the Fame of His Majeſties Grandure, that as he is the Defender of our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholical, Apoſtolical, Epiſcopal, and Proteſtantial Faith, he may ſay at the end or full Expiration of his Wars, with the holy Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8, 9. <hi>I have fought a good Fight, I have fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed my Courſe, I have kept the Faith. Henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Lord the Righteous Judge ſhall give at the laſt Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And may alſo all His Majeſties Commanders and Soldiers both by Sea and Land, Experience the Truth of my preſent Text, where it is thus expreſt by the Warlike Pſalmiſt, <hi>Through God we ſhall do valiantly: For he it is that ſhall tread down our Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:35494:17"/>
            <closer>Which God the Father of his Multitudinous Mercies grant, through the Marvellous Merits of God the Son, and the Miraculous Manifeſtations of God the Holy Ghoſt; to which Trinity in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, be aſcrib'd, as is moſt due, all Honour, Glory, Power, and Praiſe, both Now, and for Evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:35494:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOKS Printed for</hi> J. Pero, <hi>at the</hi> White Swan <hi>in</hi> Little Britain.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>JEſus</hi> is God: Or, the Deity of <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> Vindicated; being an Abſtract of ſome Sermons Preach'd in the Pariſh-Church of St. <hi>James Clerkenwell.</hi> By <hi>D. Pead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Abridgment of Chriſtian Divinity; or, True Religion and Undefiled in all its Principal and moſt Uſeful Branches; both as to Belief and Practice, briefly Stated and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to the Meaneſt Capacities. A Work Seaſonable for theſe Times, wherein ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Articles of our Faith are Queſtioned, and ſo many Groſs Errors daily Publiſhed.</p>
            <p>A Perſuaſive from the Creatures, to a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Reſignation of the Will to God's. By <hi>B. Pratt,</hi> of <hi>Merton</hi> Colledge, <hi>Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
